<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
  Copyright © 2015 <code@io7m.com> http://io7m.com

  Permission to use, copy, modify, and/or distribute this software for any
  purpose with or without fee is hereby granted, provided that the above
  copyright notice and this permission notice appear in all copies.

  THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS" AND THE AUTHOR DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES
  WITH REGARD TO THIS SOFTWARE INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
  MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR
  ANY SPECIAL, DIRECT, INDIRECT, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
  WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN
  ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUT OF
  OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE.
  -->

<s:part xmlns:s="http://schemas.io7m.com/structural/2.1.0">
  <s:part-title>Design/Rationale</s:part-title>
  <s:part-contents/>

  <s:section xml:id="rationale.problems">
    <s:section-title>Problems with OpenGL</s:section-title>
    <s:subsection>
      <s:subsection-title>Overview</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        The
        <s:term s:type="package">jcanephora</s:term>
        package takes the
        general view that OpenGL as an API is a ridiculously error-prone
        and poorly defined mess
        <s:footnote>
          Whilst, annoyingly, being the only viable cross-platform and
          vendor neutral graphics API available.
        </s:footnote>. The package attempts to address most if not all of
        the problems listed in this section.
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>
    <s:subsection xml:id="rationale.problems.types">
      <s:subsection-title>Types</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        The OpenGL API itself is weakly typed even for a C language API,
        simply exposing absolutely everything as a<s:term s:type="type">
        float</s:term>,
        <s:term s:type="type">int</s:term>, or untyped pointer. Entire classes
        of problems that should be prevented at compile time are moved to
        run-time, increasing development time, developer frustration, and
        testing burden.
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>
    <s:subsection xml:id="rationale.problems.confusion">
      <s:subsection-title>Confusion</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        Rather than add or remove function entry points, the OpenGL
        designers decided to endlessly extend existing functions with
        yet more combinations of barely-typed parameters. Actually using
        the OpenGL API correctly is a challenge even for those that are
        familiar with the full API specification. Out of the hundreds of
        thousands of combinations of parameters that can be passed to any
        given API function, only a handful are actually valid.
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>
    <s:subsection xml:id="rationale.problems.silent_failure">
      <s:subsection-title>Silent failure</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        OpenGL programs frequently fail, and when they do, they usually do
        so silently. Programmers are forced to call
        <s:term s:type="function">glGetError</s:term>
        after every API call
        if they wish to avoid this (and actually detect the error at the
        correct function call).
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>
  </s:section>

  <s:section>
    <s:section-title>Goals</s:section-title>
    <s:subsection>
      <s:subsection-title>Overview</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        Given the
        <s:link s:target="rationale.problems">problems</s:link>
        with OpenGL, the
        <s:term s:type="package">jcanephora</s:term>
        package
        has the following goals (in no particular order):
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>
    <s:subsection xml:id="rationale.goals.portability">
      <s:subsection-title>Portability</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        Programs using the
        <s:term s:type="package">jcanephora</s:term>
        APIs
        must run on as many different OpenGL implementations as possible.
        Code written using the API should be version-branch-free, and use
        only the features common to all available OpenGL implementations.
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>
    <s:subsection xml:id="rationale.goals.type_safety">
      <s:subsection-title>Type safety</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        Representing every object as an integer is unacceptable. Any
        conceptually distinct objects must be made type-incompatible,
        eliminating entire classes of bugs typical to OpenGL programs
        at compile time.
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:paragraph>
        Only the correct ways to use the API are exposed. Misuse of the API
        is simply made impossible.
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>
    <s:subsection xml:id="rationale.goals.linearity">
      <s:subsection-title>Linearity</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        Branching, version-specific code must be eliminated as far as
        is possible. Code of this type is fragile, difficult to test,
        and usually incorrect.
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>
    <s:subsection xml:id="rationale.goals.conspicuity">
      <s:subsection-title>Conspicuity of errors</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        Silent failure of programs is unacceptable. All errors that
        cannot be prevented statically must be loudly and immediately
        signalled at runtime.
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>
  </s:section>

  <s:section>
    <s:section-title>API Design</s:section-title>
    <s:subsection xml:id="rationale.solutions.capabilities">
      <s:subsection-title>Interfaces as capabilities</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        The package is written with one particular concept, throughout:
        Types represent capabilities. If the developer has a value of a
        given type, then the developer can perform all of the operations
        associated with that type.
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:paragraph>
        This is in direct contrast to the OpenGL
        API, where the developer always has full access to all API functions,
        and individual functions (or combinations of parameters to functions)
        may not work based on what the implementation supports. The emphasis
        is on <s:term s:type="emphasis">isolating the correct operations and
        statically preventing incorrect operations from occurring</s:term>.
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>

    <s:subsection xml:id="rationale.solutions.types">
      <s:subsection-title>Types</s:subsection-title>
      <s:paragraph>
        The
        <s:term s:type="package">jcanephora</s:term>
        package wraps all
        conceptually distinct objects in new types and provides sane and
        unsurprising functions to construct them. This prevents large
        classes of bugs from occurring, at compile time. It also allows
        the interfaces to be self-documenting. Consider the following
        C function prototype:
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:formal-item s:kind="examples">
        <s:formal-item-title>Weakly typed C function</s:formal-item-title>
        <s:verbatim>void _ (GLsizei, GLuint *)</s:verbatim>
      </s:formal-item>
      <s:paragraph>
        What does the function do? It could generate a set of textures
        (<s:term s:type="function">glGenTextures</s:term>), or it could
        generate a set of new buffer names
        (<s:term s:type="function">glGenBuffers</s:term>). Without carefully
        reading the documentation, the required parameters to the function
        are certainly not obvious from the type alone. Assuming the developer
        has read the documentation and worked out that the correct way to
        call the function is with the following sequence:
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:formal-item s:kind="examples">
        <s:formal-item-title>Weakly typed C calls</s:formal-item-title>
        <s:verbatim><![CDATA[GLuint texture;

glGenTextures(1, &texture);
checkGLErrors();]]></s:verbatim>
      </s:formal-item>
      <s:paragraph>
        The developer now has a value of type
        <s:term s:type="type">GLuint</s:term>. Given that many functions in
        the OpenGL API also take values of<s:term s:type="type">
        GLuint</s:term>,
        and those values have nothing to do with textures, that's a huge
        number of potential bugs that cannot be prevented by the compiler.
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:paragraph>
        The developer now wants to allocate a new RGBA texture. The
        types of the <s:term s:type="function">glTexImage2D</s:term>
        and <s:term s:type="function">glTexParameteri</s:term> functions
        are, quite frankly, insane. Almost no developer manages to use these
        functions successfully without trial and error and, naturally, all
        errors are runtime errors. Eventually, through some painful
        experimentation, the developer might stumble onto the following
        sequence of calls:
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:formal-item s:kind="examples">
        <s:formal-item-title>Allocating a texture</s:formal-item-title>
        <s:verbatim><![CDATA[GLuint texture;
void *data = makeTextureData();

glGenTextures(1, &texture);
glBindTexture(GL_TEXTURE_2D, texture);
glTexParameteri(GL_TEXTURE_2D, GL_TEXTURE_WRAP_S, GL_REPEAT);
glTexParameteri(GL_TEXTURE_2D, GL_TEXTURE_WRAP_T, GL_REPEAT);
glTexParameteri(GL_TEXTURE_2D, GL_TEXTURE_MAG_FILTER, GL_NEAREST);
glTexParameteri(GL_TEXTURE_2D, GL_TEXTURE_MIN_FILTER, GL_NEAREST);
glTexImage2D(GL_TEXTURE_2D, 0, GL_RGBA8, 256, 256, 0, GL_RGBA, GL_UNSIGNED_BYTE, data);]]></s:verbatim>
      </s:formal-item>
      <s:paragraph>
        The types of the parameters to all of the functions mentioned allow
        the developer to pass in practically anything. Only a very small
        subset of the possible parameters are actually valid. An even
        smaller subset of the possible parameters actually work across
        different versions of OpenGL!
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:paragraph>
        Now consider the
        following <s:term s:type="package">jcanephora</s:term> function:
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:formal-item s:kind="examples">
        <s:formal-item-title>Texture allocation?</s:formal-item-title>
        <s:verbatim><![CDATA[public JCGLTexture2DType _(
    JCGLTextureUnitType _,
    long _,
    long _,
    JCGLTextureFormat _,
    JCGLTextureWrapS _,
    JCGLTextureWrapT _,
    JCGLTextureFilterMinification _,
    JCGLTextureFilterMagnification _)
    throws JCGLException;]]></s:verbatim>
      </s:formal-item>
      <s:paragraph>
        Even without the names of the function and the parameters,
        the type above make it quite clear that the function returns a
        <s:term s:type="type">JCGLTexture2DType</s:term>, which is somehow
        derived from the arguments to the function. It's a reasonable
        assumption to make that the function allocates a new texture.
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:paragraph>
        The wrapping modes on the <s:term s:type="constant">S</s:term> and
        <s:term s:type="constant">T</s:term> axis will presumably be
        derived from the parameters of type
        <s:term s:type="type">JCGLTextureWrapS</s:term> and
        <s:term s:type="type">JCGLTextureWrapT</s:term> respectively. The
        minification and magnification filters will presumably be derived
        from the parameters of type
        <s:term s:type="type">JCGLTextureFilterMinification</s:term> and
        <s:term s:type="type">JCGLTextureFilterMagnification</s:term>,
        respectively. The programmer is statically prevented from mixing
        up the two axes, or the two filter domains. The
        <s:term s:type="type">JCGLTextureFormat</s:term> parameter is
        obviously intended to specify the format of the texture. Any
        parameter familiar with OpenGL texturing will be aware that any
        operations involving textures requires access to a
        <s:term s:type="term">texture unit</s:term>, and the
        <s:term s:type="type">JCGLTextureUnitType</s:term> parameter
        above presumably specifies the unit that will be used.
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:paragraph>
        The two parameters of type <s:term s:type="type">long</s:term>
        presumably correspond to the width and height of the resulting
        texture, but the types are not descriptive enough to say for sure.
        Unfortunately, Java lacks a way to make existing arithmetic types
        incompatible without sacrificing efficiency
        <s:footnote>
          New types will be new classes, resulting in all integers being
          replaced with pointers to integers.
        </s:footnote>. In this case, the two parameters do indeed
        correspond to the width and height, in that order, and the
        <s:term s:type="package">jcanephora</s:term> package uses this
        order consistently throughout.
      </s:paragraph>
      <s:paragraph>
        The extremely descriptive type given for the function, and the
        presence of declared (but unchecked) exceptions are direct contributions
        towards the goals of
        <s:link s:target="rationale.goals.type_safety">type safety</s:link>
        and
        <s:link s:target="rationale.goals.conspicuity">conspicuity of errors</s:link>.
        It is very difficult for the programmer to use this function
        incorrectly: the type system guarantees correct usage.
      </s:paragraph>
    </s:subsection>
  </s:section>

</s:part>
